# Michael K. Mabey

(480) 788-3411 ♦ mmabey@asu.edu ♂ ♦ mikemabey.com ♂



#### **EDUCATION**

PhD Computer Science — Information Assurance	(expected) May 2017
Arizona State University	Tempe, AZ

Research Topics: Email forensics, Chrome OS forensics, Collaborative forensics

# M.S. Computer Science — Information Assurance

Aug 2011

Arizona State University

Tempe, AZ

Committee: Gail-Joon Ahn (Chair), Stephen S. Yau, Dijiang Huang

In order to catch the smartest criminals in the world, digital forensic examiners need a means of collaborating and sharing information that is not prohibitively difficult to use and that complies with standard operating procedures and the rules of evidence. In this work I present the design and implementation of the Collaborative Forensic Framework (CUFF) which is a cloud-based forensic analysis environment that facilitates collaboration among examiners and their trusted colleagues. CUFF makes a positive impact on forensic examiners' efficiency by helping them leverage their network of subject matter experts while also tapping into the scalability and power of the cloud.

# B.S. Computer Science — Information Systems

May 2009

**Utah State University** 

Logan, UT

Albuquerque, NM

# **EXPERIENCE SUMMARY**

Sandia National Laboratories

Research Assistant Security Engineering for Future Computing (SEFCOM) Lab Lab Directors: Gail-Joon Ahn, Adam Doupé	Nov 2009 − Present a, ASU Tempe, AZ
Civilian Reserve/Intern Arizona Department of Public Safety	<i>May 2016 – Aug 2016</i> Phoenix, AZ
<b>Teaching Assistant</b> Arizona State University	<i>Aug 2010 – Dec 2015</i> Tempe, AZ
SAT/ACT Instructor Minerva Learning, LLC	Sep 2015 – Oct 2015 Chandler, AZ
Summer Intern Arizona Cyber Threat Response Alliance (ACTRA)	<i>Jul 2015 – Sep 2015</i> Phoenix, AZ
<b>Teaching Assistant (Instructor of Record)</b> Arizona State University	<i>Aug 2011 – Dec 2014</i> Tempe, AZ
Student Trainee (Civilian) US Army	Jun 2013 – Aug 2013, Jun 2014 – Aug 2014 Fort Meade, MD
Graduate Student Summer Intern	May 2011 – Jul 2011

Graduate Student Recruitment Specialist/Webmaster *Jul 2006 – Aug 2009* Electrical & Computer Engineering Department, USU Logan, UT Sep 2006 - Aug 2009 Technician Aid Electrical & Computer Engineering Department, USU Logan, UT Store Attendant Jun 2005 - Sep 2008 Electrical & Computer Engineering Department, USU Logan, UT May 1997 - Aug 2002 Lab Technician KWM Electronics Co. West Jordan, UT

#### HONORS AND AWARDS

DoD Information Assurance Scholarship Program (IASP) Recipient (4 years)
 Inducted into Eta Kappa Nu (HKN) Engineering Honors Society
 Eagle Scout, Boy Scouts of America

#### RESEARCH INTERESTS

· Digital Forensics

Web and Email Forensics

Forensics on Non-Traditional Devices

Cyber Security

Threat Intelligence Sharing

Web Security

## **RESEARCH EXPERIENCE**

Research Assistant

Security Engineering for Future Computing (SEFCOM) Lab &, ASU

Nov 2009 – Present
Tempe, AZ

Lab Directors: Gail-Joon Ahn, Adam Doupé

· Projects:

 Researched forensic techniques for Chrome OS/Chromium OS by creating tools in Python and using libvirt to interface with a KVM/QEMU hypervisor. (In progress)

Publications: [S1], [P1], [BL1], [BL2]

• Developed a web email forensic acquisition approach that reestablishes persistent cookie sessions stored by a browser, and automated the process using **Python** and **Selenium**. *Publications:* [C1]

• Designed and implemented the core components of a modular, highly scalable, collaboration-centric digital forensic framework built on the **OpenStack** cloud architecture. Functions of the components included distributed job scheduling, storage management, and concise evidence representation and transmission.

Publications: [C3], [J2], [P3]

Sponsors

 Department of Defense Information Assurance Scholarship Program (IASP)

- Department of Energy
- National Science Foundation

## **PUBLICATIONS**

## Peer-Reviewed Conference Proceedings

[C1] Justin Paglierani, Mike Mabey, and Gail-Joon Ahn. "Towards Comprehensive and Collaborative Forensics on Email Evidence". In: Collaborative Computing: Networking, Applications and Worksharing (Collaboratecom), 2013 9th International Conference Conference on. October 2013, pp. 11–20. DOI: 10.4108/icst.collaboratecom.2013.254125 c.

Mabey Revised 08/04/2016 2

- [C2] Wonkyu Han, **Mike Mabey**, and Gail-Joon Ahn. "Simulation-Based Validation for Smart Grid Environments". In: *Information Reuse and Integration (IRI), 2013 IEEE 14th International Conference on.* August 2013, pp. 14–21. DOI: 10.1109/IRI.2013.6642448 ♂.
- [C3] **Mike Mabey** and Gail-Joon Ahn. "Towards Collaborative Forensics: Preliminary Framework". In: *Information Reuse and Integration (IRI), 2011 IEEE International Conference on.* August 2011, pp. 94–99. DOI: 10.1109/IRI.2011.6009527 &.

# Peer-Reviewed Book Chapters & Journal Papers

- [J1] Wonkyu Han, **Mike Mabey**, Gail-Joon Ahn, and Tae Sung Kim. "Simulation-Based Validation for Smart Grid Environments: Framework and Experimental Results". In: *Integration of Reusable Systems*. Ed. by Thouraya Bouabana-Tebibel and Stuart H. Rubin. Vol. 263. Advances in Intelligent Systems and Computing. (Extended version of [C2]). Springer International Publishing, 2014, pp. 27–44. ISBN: 978-3-319-04716-4. DOI: 10.1007/978-3-319-04717-1\_2 ♂.
- [J2] **Mike Mabey** and Gail-Joon Ahn. "Towards Collaborative Forensics". In: *Information Reuse and Integration in Academia and Industry*. Ed. by Tansel Özyer, Keivan Kianmehr, Mehmet Tan, and Jia Zeng. (Extended version of [C3]). Springer Vienna, 2013, pp. 237–260. ISBN: 978-3-7091-1537-4. DOI: 10.1007/978-3-7091-1538-1\_12 ☑.

## **Poster Presentations**

- [P1] Mike Mabey, Jeremy Whitaker, Gail-Joon Ahn, and Adam Doupé. *Towards Forensics for Web Thin Clients. Symposium on Information Assurance Research and Education, ASU*. November 2015.
- [P2] Jeremy Whitaker, **Mike Mabey**, Gail-Joon Ahn, and Adam Doupé. *Forensic Analysis on Mobile Devices*. *Symposium on Information Assurance Research and Education, ASU*. October 2014.
- [P3] **Mike Mabey**, Justin Paglierani, and Gail-Joon Ahn. *Towards Collaborative Forensics*. *Workshop on Information Assurance Research and Education, ASU*. April 2012.

# Works Submitted (In Press)

[S1] Mike Mabey, Adam Doupé, Ziming Zhao, and Gail-Joon Ahn. "dbling: Identifying Extensions Installed on Encrypted Web Thin Clients". In: *Digital Investigation* (2016). The Proceedings of the Sixteenth Annual DFRWS Conference (In Press). DOI: 10.1016/j.diin.2016.04.007 ♂.

# **TEACHING INTERESTS**

- · Computer and Network Forensics
- · Advanced Topics in Digital Forensics
- · Information Assurance

- · Security Toolkit Programming with Python
- Cryptography
- Software Security

# **TEACHING EXPERIENCE**

# **Teaching Assistant**

Aug 2010 - Dec 2015

Tempe, AZ

Arizona State University

- $\cdot$  CSE 465 Information Assurance with Dr. Gail-Joon Ahn: Fall 2010, Fall 2015.
- · CSE 469 Computer and Network Forensics with Dr. Gail-Joon Ahn: Spring 2015.
- FSE 100 Introduction to Engineering with Dr. Ryan Meuth: Spring 2014.
- · CSE 423/424 Capstone I and CSE 485/486 Capstone II with Dr. Debra Calliss: Spring 2014.
- · CSE 467 Data & Information Security with Dr. Gail-Joon Ahn: Spring 2011.

# **SAT/ACT Instructor** Minerva Learning, LLC

Sep 2015 - Oct 2015

Chandler, AZ

Individual tutor for a high school student preparing for the PSAT.

Mabey Revised 08/04/2016 3

## Teaching Assistant (Instructor of Record)

Arizona State University

Aug 2011 – Dec 2014 Tempe, AZ

· CSE 465 Information Assurance: Fall 2014.

• FSE 100 Introduction to Engineering: Fall 2011 – Fall 2013 (5 semesters).

#### **TECHNICAL STRENGTHS & QUALIFICATIONS**

Programming Languages Python, C/C++, HTML, CSS, LATEX

**Forensic Tools** FTK, Sleuth Kit & Autopsy, dd, HxD, etc.

Protocols & APIs

JSON, XML, REST, STIX/TAXII, Protocol Buffers

Network Administration/Security

OpenVPN, Wireshark, ufw, Apache, lighttpd

Operating Systems Windows, Linux, Chrome OS

**Databases** MySQL, SQLite

#### **SERVICE**

# Department

Team Leader: ASU team in the UCSB International CTF
 Panelist: PhD Open House Student Panel
 2009, 2010, 2014, 2015
 Feb 2014, Feb 2015

#### **Profession**

· Student Program Committee Member:

• IEEE Security & Privacy 2016

· Conference Proceedings Subreviewer:

• ACM CODASPY 2013, 2014, 2015, 2016

• SACMAT 2014

• ASIACCS 2014

· Student Volunteer:

• ACM CCS 2014

## **Technical Blog Posts**

- [BL1] **Mike Mabey**. How to check out an old version of Chromium OS. http://mikemabey.blogspot.com/ 2016/02/how-to-check-out-old-version-of.html @. February 26, 2016.
- [BL2] **Mike Mabey**. *Fixing repo init to check out Chromium OS code*. http://mikemabey.blogspot.com/2015/01/fixing-repo-init-to-check-out-chromium.html \( \mathref{c} \). January 30, 2015.
- [BL3] **Mike Mabey**. *Getting into Developer Mode on the HP Pavilion 14 Chromebook*. http://mikemabey.blogspot.com/2013/05/getting-into-developer-mode-on-hp.html @. May 8, 2013.
- [BL4] **Mike Mabey**. *OpenVPN Update: Fixed!* http://mikemabey.blogspot.com/2012/06/openvpn-update-fixed.html \( \varphi \). June 6, 2012.
- [BL5] **Mike Mabey**. *Debian on Android and my quest for a full-fledged terminal Python IDE*. http://mikemabey.blogspot.com/2012/06/debian-on-android-and-my-quest-for-full.html & June 23, 2012.

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

## Civilian Reserve/Intern

May 2016 - Aug 2016

Arizona Department of Public Safety

Phoenix, AZ

- · Updated the content, layout, and topics of the security policy for the Arizona Counter Terrorism Information Center (ACTIC) for clarity and to be in compliance with recommendations from the Department of Homeland Security.
- · Created training slides to accompany the new security policy.

Summer Intern Jul 2015 – Sep 2015

Arizona Cyber Threat Response Alliance (ACTRA)

Phoenix, AZ

• Designed an operationalized workflow for AZ Infragard member organizations to share **threat intelliquence** through a common **STIX/TAXII** platform.

Student Trainee (Civilian)

Jun 2013 - Aug 2013, Jun 2014 - Aug 2014

**US Army** 

Fort Meade, MD

· Summer internships in connection with DoD IASP scholarship.

# **Graduate Student Summer Intern**

May 2011 - Jul 2011

Sandia National Laboratories

Albuquerque, NM

- Helped design a dynamic malware analysis framework built on OpenStack, allowing incident responders to define customizable analysis environments and use arbitrary analysis tools in triage or manual analysis mode.
- · Wrote **Python** scripts to automate the setup process for using a SheevaPlug computer as a wireless intrusion detection agent running **Kismet**.

# Graduate Student Recruitment Specialist/Webmaster

Jul 2006 - Aug 2009

Electrical & Computer Engineering Department, USU

Logan, UT

- Primary responsibilities included maintaining and augmenting the department website using PHP, MySQL, and other basic web technologies like CSS, JavaScript, and an SMTP server.
- · Completed multiple graphics design projects for the department using **Photoshop**, **Illustrator**, and **GIMP**.
- Replaced a MS Access database by porting the old data to a MySQL server and creating a set of Python
  programs with the Dabo framework that interfaced with the database.
- · Created a testing environment using an Apache web server, PHP, MySQL, and SVN.
- Gathered statistics on web visitors, inquiries from students, and applicants' credentials for the purpose of improving graduate student recruitment processes for the department.
- · Responded to inquiries from potential domestic and international graduate students.

Technician Aid Sep 2006 – Aug 2009

Electrical & Computer Engineering Department, USU

Logan, UT

- · Built and maintained computers for department faculty and student labs.
- · Installed and configured various software on Windows machines for faculty, staff, and students.
- · Created and restored backup images of lab computers using **Norton Ghost** and **Acronis Truelmage**.
- · Protected lab computers using Faronics Deep Freeze.

Store Attendant Jun 2005 – Sep 2008

Electrical & Computer Engineering Department, USU

Logan, UT

- · Maintained equipment and instruments in the labs for electrical engineering students.
- Performed store duties including maintaining inventory, serving customers, cleaning rooms, and running errands.

Lab Technician May 1997 – Aug 2002

KWM Electronics Co. West Jordan, UT

- Worked closely with CEO/Head Engineer to build prototypes of electronic devices.
- · Used various soldering techniques on both through-hole and surface-mount parts.

Mabey Revised 08/04/2016 5

#### PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIPS

· IEEE (Student Member)

· IEEE Computer Society

## PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

Preparing Future Faculty (GRD 791 at ASU)

Aug 2015 - Present

The Preparing Future Faculty (PFF) program is a year-long series of seminars, discussions and activities designed to expose graduate students and postdocs more fully to the realities of teaching, research and service in higher education.

#### **REFERENCES**

Please feel free to contact any of my references.

## Gail-Joon Ahn

Professor of Computer Science and Engineering

Fulton Entrepreneurial Professor

School of Computing, Informatics and Decision Systems Engineering

Ira A. Fulton Schools of Engineering, Arizona State University

Brickyard Engineering (BYENG) Bldg, Room 486

699 S. Mill Avenue

Tempe, AZ 85281

Phone: (480) 965-9007 Fax: (480) 965-2751

http://www.public.asu.edu/~gahn1/&

gahn@asu.edu@

## Adam Doupé

Assistant Professor of Computer Science and Engineering

School of Computing, Informatics and Decision Systems Engineering

Ira A. Fulton Schools of Engineering, Arizona State University

Brickyard Engineering (BYENG) Bldg, Room 472

699 S. Mill Avenue

Tempe, AZ 85281

Fax: (480) 965-2751 http://adamdoupe.com ♂

doupe@asu.edu&

## Frank J. Grimmelmann

President & CEO/Intelligence Liaison Officer

Arizona Cyber Threat Response Alliance (ACTRA)

Phone: (623) 551-1526 Fax: (623) 551-4221

fgrimmelmann@actraaz.org@

# Stephen S. Yau

Director, Information Assurance Center 
Professor of Computer Science and Engineering
School of Computing, Informatics and Decision Systems Engineering
Ira A. Fulton Schools of Engineering, Arizona State University
Brickyard Engineering (BYENG) Bldg, Room 488
699 S. Mill Avenue

Tempe, AZ 85281

Phone: (480) 965-2647 Fax: (480) 965-2751

http://dpse.eas.asu.edu/yau/♂

yau@asu.edu ♂